<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The way to well-doing. Or A sermon of faith and good vvorkes Preached in the chappell of Buntingford, in the county of Hartford, at the beginning of their publike lecture. By Iohn Gore, rector of Wenden-lofts in Essex.</title>
            <author>Gore, John, Rector of Wendenlofts, Essex.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116024</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851241</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851241</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16509</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68105)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16509)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1547:06, 1687:04, 1687:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The way to well-doing. Or A sermon of faith and good vvorkes Preached in the chappell of Buntingford, in the county of Hartford, at the beginning of their publike lecture. By Iohn Gore, rector of Wenden-lofts in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Gore, John, Rector of Wendenlofts, Essex.</author>
                  <author>Gore, John, Rector of Wendenlofts, Essex, Summer sermon. aut</author>
                  <author>Gore, John, Rector of Wendenlofts, Essex. Winter sermon. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Cotes, for Thomas Alchorn, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Greene-Dragon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also issued as part of his "Certayn sermons", 1639 (STC 12071.5).</note>
                  <note>In three parts, each with separate dated title pages and pagination; signatures continuous.</note>
                  <note>Part 2, "A summer sermon", is formerly STC 12077 and part 3, "A winter sermon", is formerly STC 12089.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1687 #4 (part 1 only), at reel 1687 #5 (part 3 only, identified as STC 12089) and at reel 1547 #6 (part 2 only, identified as STC 12077).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16509:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A
SVMMER
SERMON
VPON
ELIAHS PRAYER.
Preached in the</hi> Cathedrall Church <hi>of
St.</hi> Pauls <hi>in LONDON,</hi> on the laſt Sonday of
<hi>Trinity Terme</hi> in the afternoone, being a time
of extraordinary heat and drought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> John Gore, <hi>Rector of</hi> Wenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lofts
in Eſſex.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Thomas Cotes,</hi> for <hi>Themas Alchorn,</hi>
and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at
the Signe of the <hi>Greene-Dragon. 1638.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16509:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16509:2"/>
            <head>TO
THE RIGHT
WORSHIPF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.
VVILLIAM BIRD, Doctor of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill
Law, my moſt Worthy Friend
and Benefactor.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT WORSHIP.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I conſider the manifold fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
and courteſies that I have
found at your hands, I am ready
to ſay unto my ſelfe, as <hi>Ruth</hi> ſaid
once to <hi>Boaz, Ruth 2. 10. Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
inveni gratiam?</hi> Why have I found grace
in your eyes, that you ſhould take knowledge of me,
ſeeing I am a ſtranger? For mine owne part I
can impute it to nothing, but unto Gods goodneſſe,
and your owne worthineſſe: And my onely ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
is to make you this acknowledgement that the
<pb facs="tcp:16509:3"/>
world may ſee, though I am poore, I am thankefull.
Now as <hi>Ioab</hi> wiſht to <hi>David</hi> in another caſe, <hi>2
Sam. 24. 3.</hi> ſo wiſh I to you, The Lord God adde
unto your eſtate, how much ſoever it be, an hundred
fold, and that your eyes may ſee it, and your heart
may rejoyce in it all the dayes of your life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thus prayes<lb/>
Your poore unworthy<lb/>
Friend,<lb/>
JOHN GORE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16509:3"/>
            <head>A
SVMMER
SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>IAMES 5. 17, 18.</bibl>
               <q>Elias was a man ſubject to like paſsions as wee are, and
hee prayed earneſtly that it might not raine, and it
rained not on the earth by the ſpace of three yeares
and ſixe moneths. And hee prayed againe, and
the heavens gave raine, and the earth brought forth
her fruit.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſumme and drift of this Text
is to ſet forth the efficacie, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
omnipotency of earneſt
and fervent Prayer. There be
two graces of God in man, that
may juſtly be termed Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
or Almighty graces; God
himſelfe being pleaſed to ſhew his Almighty power
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16509:4"/>
and goodneſſe in them, and they are <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
1. For the firſt, <hi>Mat. 15. 28. O woman great is
thy faith, bee it unto thee even as thou wilt.</hi> What a
large unlimitted Grant and Patent was this for a
poore ſinner to aske what ſhe would, and have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
of acceptance. <hi>Mark. 9. 23. To him that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
all things are poſsible.</hi> Looke what a beleever
cannot doe himſelfe, God himſelfe will doe it for
him, and yet it ſhal be accounted as his act and deed.
<hi>Phil. 4. 13. I can doe all things through Chriſt that
ſtrengtheneth me:</hi> Not meaning that hee could doe
all things in generall and at large, as to walke on the
waters, flye in the ayre, &amp;c. but all things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed
to his calling, all things that concerned his
Miniſtery, and all things that pertained to the right
way of pleaſing God and of ſaving his owne ſoule:
He could pray well, Preach well, live well; he could
want and he could abound, he could conforme and
apply himſelfe to all eſtates whatſoever: All this
hee could doe, not by any power or ability of his
owne, but by the ſtrengthning grace, and faith, and
vertue of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>(I can doe all things through
Chriſt that ſtrengthneth me.)</hi> As on the contrary, our
Saviour ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>Mark. 6. 5.</hi> that he could
doe nothing worth ſpeaking of in his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>no mighty worke,</hi> no worke of
wonder (in reſpect of what he could have done) on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<hi>becauſe of their unbeleife:</hi> and marke, that it is not
ſaid, <hi>He would</hi> do no ſuch workes there, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>He could</hi> not doe them: not that Chriſt was unable
for want of power, but hee ſaw it was unavaileable
through their lacke of faith. For the power of God,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16509:4"/>
and the faith of men, are like the ſpirits and the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes
in the body, the one mooves, and ſtirres, and
workes within the other; if there be no faith in us,
there can be no expectation of any power or any
helpe from God.</p>
            <p>2. The other omnipotent grace is <hi>Prayer;</hi> and that
you may be aſſured it is ſo, marke but that expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<hi>Exod. 32. 10. Let me alone</hi> (ſaith God to <hi>Moſes)
that I may conſume them, and I will make of thee a great
Nation.</hi> What a word was this to come from the
mouth of Almighty God, to bid a poore weake
creature, <hi>let him alone:</hi> it ſhewes that <hi>Moſes</hi> by his
prayer did even (as it were) <hi>over-power</hi> the Lord,
that the Lord had not the power to revenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
on that provoking people, as long as <hi>Moſes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceded
for them.</p>
            <p>Such a powerfull man with God was <hi>Eliah</hi> here
in my text: His mouth (as a Father ſaith) was <hi>Frae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num
Coeli,</hi> the very bridle of Heaven; he could even
rule the heavens with his prayers, as a man rules a
horſe with a bridle: Now leaſt you ſhould thinke
he did thus prevaile with God, rather by the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of his perſon, than by the vertue of his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
The Apoſtle tells us for that, he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he
was a man ſubject to the ſame paſsions that we are,</hi> and
yet his prayer tooke ſuch good effect. <hi>(Eliah was a
man ſubject, &amp;c.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In my text there are two generall points to bee
conſidered. 1. The condition and quality of <hi>Eliahs</hi>
perſon, <hi>[He was a man ſubject to like paſsions as wee
are]</hi> 2. The condition and quality of his prayer;
that like a two-edged ſword, it cut both wayes, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16509:5"/>
prevailed in both kindes; both to bring a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and to bring a bleſſing upon the people. His
firſt prayer like a burning feaver entred into the
bowels of the earth, and ſcorcht and dryed up the
Rivers and Lakes, and Springs, and left no moiſture
in them; and ſo brought a judgement of drought and
dearth upon the land. His ſecond prayer went up
into the clouds above, and fetcht an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a
<hi>heaven-dropping dew,</hi> a happy and a heavenly raine
that moyſtned and fatned, and refreſhed the earth
againe <hi>[He prayed againe, and the heavens gave raine,
and the earth brought forth her fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. The condition and quality of <hi>Eliahs</hi> perſon,
what manner of man <hi>Eliah</hi> was? My Text ſaith hee
was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>A man ſubject to the ſame paſsions,</hi> to
the ſame frailties and infirmities <hi>that we are.</hi> Hence
you may obſerve, that no profeſſion of holineſſe,
no practiſe of piety, no degree of grace and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
in this life, can exempt, or free, or priviledge
a man from common paſſions, and infirmities, <hi>Eliah</hi>
was a man of God, a mortified and a ſanctified man,
and one of the greateſt favourites in the Court of
heaven, and yet a man ſubject to paſſions. What
ſhall I neede to multiply examples to proove this
point, when wee know the Apoſtle affirmeth even
of our Saviour himſelfe, <hi>That hee was in all things
like unto us ſinne onely excepted:</hi> ſet but ſinne aſide
(where of his bleſſed perſon was uncapable, for as
no ruſt can take hold of burning and flaming iron;
no more could any ſin or corruption take hold of his
pure and precious ſoule) ſet but that aſide, and our
Saviour Chriſt was (as <hi>Eliah</hi> is ſaid to be) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16509:5"/>
man ſubject to the very ſame infirmities and paſsions,</hi> of
anger, and feare, and ſorrow, and ſadneſſe, <hi>that wee
are:</hi> and happy was it for us that ſo he was; for by
this meanes he became (as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb. 2.
17. A mercifull High-Prieſt,)</hi> one that knew how
to tender and ſuccour our infirmities, becauſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
had a feeling of them in his owne nature. This
made him ſo tenderly affected towards the hungry
multitude, <hi>Mat. 15.</hi> becauſe himſelfe knew by his
owne experience what an unſufferable miſery hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
was. This made him ſo compaſſionate towards
the ſorrowes of <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Martha, Iohn 11.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
himſelfe was <hi>Vir dolorum, a man acquainted
with griefe and ſorrow:</hi> And ſuch was his compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
toward <hi>Peter</hi> in that ſtate of deſertion wherein
he lay, <hi>Luke 22.</hi> becauſe himſelfe knew and felt in
his owne ſoule, what a woefull thing it was to be
forſaken of God. And this is the aſſurance which
the Apoſtle gives us, that wee ſhall obtaine mercy
and grace from Ieſus Chriſt, to helpe and comfort
us in time of neede, <hi>Heb. 4. 16.</hi> becauſe himſelfe
had a feeling of the ſame infirmities, and was a man
ſubject to the ſame paſſions that wee our ſelves are,
ſinne onely excepted.</p>
            <p>In a word then, as there is no Roſe ſince the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
but hath his prickles, as well as his ſweete
leaves; ſo there is no man living ſince the fall of
<hi>Adam,</hi> (except our Saviour forementioned, who
was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man</hi> both) but hath his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
as well as his perfections, his infirmities as well
as his graces. As <hi>Cyril</hi> obſerves, there is no Rocke
of ſtone ſo hard, but hath ſome crackes, ſome clefts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16509:6"/>
and ſeames in it, whereat weedes ſpring out and
grow: ſo there is no mans heart ſo ſanctified and
filled with grace, but hath ſome crackes, ſome flawes
in it, whereat his ſinnes and corruptions ſprout and
iſſue out, to his no ſmall regret and greife. And as
we ſee by experience, that there is chaffe about eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
corne in the field, and bitterneſſe in every branch
of Wormewood, and ſaltneſſe in every drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
in the Sea: ſo is there infirmity and frailty, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
and paſſion in every man, woman, and child,
of what eſtate, of what degree, of what profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
ſoever. <hi>Eliah was</hi> a holy man, a zealous
man, a man of God, and yet <hi>a man ſubject to paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let no man therefore be too forward or too ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere
in cenſuring and condemning the follies and
frailties, the weakeneſſes and paſſions of godly men,
or of the men of God, (ſuch as <hi>Eliah</hi> was) for alas,
they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſubject to the ſame paſſions that
other men are, <hi>Solomon</hi> tels us, <hi>Pro. 27, 19, That as in
water, face anſwereth to face, ſo doth the heart of man
to man.</hi> A man that lookes into the water, or into a
glaſſe, ſhall ſee a face there in all points anſwering to
his owne, the ſame ſpots, the ſame warts, the ſame
wrinkles and blemiſhes that he ſees in the face in the
water; they are all the very ſame in his owne face,
there is face anſwering to face, ſo doth the heart of
man to man; the ſame evils, the ſame corruptions,
luſts and ſins, that thou ſeeſt in another mans heart,
breaking out into his life, the very ſelfe-ſame are in
thy owne heart; his heart to thine is but as a face
anſwering to a face in the water. Obſerve the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16509:6"/>
demand, <hi>1 Cor. 4. 7.</hi> and apply it to thy ſelfe
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? <hi>Who makes thee to differ from another man?</hi>
For by nature all are alike, all equally devoid of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
grace and goodneſſe, and all equally prone to
ſinne and wickedneſſe: how comes it to paſſe then,
that one man differs from another, that one is holy,
blameleſſe, and undefiled in his way; another li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious
and looſe, and ſpotted with the world?
Anſwer, It is not any thing in nature (beleeve that
for a truth) but meerely that ſame <hi>Gratia diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans</hi>
(as Divines call it) that <hi>diſtinguiſhing Grace</hi> of
God, it is that which makes the difference betwixt
one man and another. Let no man therefore aſcribe
any thing to himſelfe for his freedome from great
offences, but give God the glory of his grace which
had made him to differ from the greateſt ſinner, and
if at any time, thou ſeeſt another man breake out
into paſſion, or miſcarry in his way by ſome ill
temptation; reprove him in Gods name; and pray
for him when thou haſt done, and withall, reflect
upon thy ſelfe, and ſay, as <hi>Plato</hi> did, <hi>Num ego talis
uſpiam? Am not I ſuch a one?</hi> Have not I beene, or
may not I be as vile and as vicious as hee? Be not
therefore too cenſorious nor too ſupercilious (as the
manner of ſome is) but incline rather to thinke eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
man better, than to thinke any man worſe than
thy ſelfe: if thou ſeeſt thy brother <hi>overtaken in a
fault,</hi> doe then as the Apoſtle adviſeth thee, <hi>Gal.
6. 1.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>reſtore him with the ſpirit of meckeneſſe,</hi>
or (as the word ſignifieth) bind him up gently and
lovingly, as a Chirurgian doth a bone that is out of
joynt; <hi>Conſidering thy ſelfe</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>leaſt thou
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16509:7"/>
alſo be tempted;</hi> conſidering (I ſay) that thou art, as
he is, and all men are, as <hi>Eliah</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, too like
one another in that which is naught, all ſubject to
the ſame paſſions; <hi>All</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>ſhut up
under ſinne,</hi> And I pray God of his goodneſſe have
mercy on us all, Amen.</p>
            <p>Againe, the conſideration of this, if it be rightly
conceived, may ſerve for a comfort and a ſtay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
ſuch tender conſciences as have ſinned of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,
and like <hi>Moſes</hi> in their haſte, have ſpoken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedly
with their lips, not being able for the
time to over-rule and bridle their paſſions. It is ſome
comfort to conſider, that the greateſt Saints of
God have ſometimes beene of the ſame temper;
yea there is not a ſoule in heaven (the ſoule of Ieſus
Chriſt onely excepted) but hath beene ſometimes
ſubject to the very ſame paſſions. <hi>And I ſaid, This is
my infirmity</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>Pſal. 77. 10. but I
remember the yeares of the right hand of the moſt
High. i.</hi> I conſider and call to minde that God in
former times, and in the dayes of old, hath had
compaſſion upon the ſame infirmities in other men;
and why ſhould I miſdoubt (he being ſtill the ſame
compaſſionate God) but that hee will have pitty
and compaſſion upon the ſame infirmities in me. But
ſome man may ſay: How ſhall I know and be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
that my ſinnes are ſinnes of infirmity, ſuch as
God will winke at; and not rather ſinnes of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption
and iniquity, ſuch as his ſoule abhorres?
Anſwer, A ſinne of infirmity may be knowne two
wayes.</p>
            <p>1. By the antecedent which goes before it; and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16509:7"/>
that is an honeſt reſolution of a mans heart againſt
ſinne and evill; when a man doth ſtedfaſtly reſolve
(by the aſſiſtance and grace of God) to ſeparate
himſelfe from every knowne ſinne, and to ſanctifie
himſelfe in all holy duty and obedience to God,
ſtriving by a holy deſire and an hearty endeavour, in
nothing willingly to ſinne againſt God, but in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
thing to pleaſe him and approove himſelfe unto
him: if ſuch a man chance to fall by occaſion into
a fault, or be overtaken unawares (as the Apoſtle
ſpeakes, <hi>Gal. 6. 1.)</hi> beſides the purpoſe of his heart,
and the intention and deſire of his ſoule: that mans
ſinnes, are ſinnes of infirmity, which by the mercy
of God ſhall never be laid to his charge. Contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
when a man ſhall hang <hi>in equilibrio,</hi> in an even
ballance (as it were) betwixt wickedneſſe and
goodneſſe, and ſhall be equally diſpoſed to ſinne or
not to ſinne as occaſion ſhall offer it ſelfe; or which
is worſe, ſhall doe like him, <hi>Pſal. 36. 4.</hi> ſhall ſet, and
ſettle himſelfe in a way that is not good, reſolving
with himſelfe, that this ſinne fits my turne, and
pleaſeth my humour, and I will not part with it: or
which is worſt of all, when a man ſhall <hi>draw iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
with cords of vanity</hi> (as the Prophet ſpeaketh) as
if the devill were backeward, and ſinne would not
come faſt enough upon him of its owne accord;
ſhall fiſh and angle for it, and hunt after ill compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
and draw himſelfe and others into ſinne, as Fiſh
and Fowles are drawne into a net, to their ruine and
deſtruction; this mans ſinnes are farre beyond the
ſinne of infirmity, for they are ſinnes of iniquity,
and ſinnes of obſtinacy, and ſuch as will coſt him
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16509:8"/>
many a ſigh, many a groane, many a teare, before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
he ſhall attaine to this comfortable perſwaſion,
that there is compaſſion with God, and ſalvation
with Chriſt for his ſoule.</p>
            <p>2. A ſinne of infirmity is knowne by the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents
of it, or that which followes after it: it leaves
ſuch a ſting behind it in the ſoule, that a man can
never be at quiet in his owne conſcience, till he hath
made his peace with God by a ſound and ſerious
humiliation, and reconciled himſelfe againe to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt. Yea, it never leaves a man, till it hath
brought him to that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
which the Apoſtle ſpeakes of, <hi>2 Cor. 7. 11.</hi> that
a man ſhall even fret and vexe and fall out with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
for offending and provoking ſo good, ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
a God. It will make a man upbraid himſelfe for
a very beaſt and a foole (as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Pſal. 73.) So
ignorant was I, and ſo fooliſh, even as a beaſt before thee.</hi>
And it is a ſure rule, that of Saint <hi>Auguſtine; Pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta
non nocent, ſi non placent; if a mans ſinnes doe not
pleaſe him, they will never hurt him.</hi> Whereas on the
contrary, when a man can carry away his ſinnes as
lightly as <hi>Sampſon</hi> carryed the gates of <hi>Azza,</hi> that
they are no burthen to his ſoule; or if they doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne
to trouble him, ſhall doe as <hi>Saul</hi> did, betake
himſelfe to muſicke and ſport, and merry company
to drive it away (as if one ſinne could drive out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and not rather drive it further in:) beleeve
it, this mans ſinnes are no ſinnes of infirmity, but
they are ſinnes of an higher nature, and ſuch as will
coſt a man deare ere he can be acquitted of them in
the ſight of God. And this I dare confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16509:8"/>
that there is no man that ſinnes of infirmity,
but he is afterward the better for his ſinne; it makes
him the more jealous of himſelfe, the more watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
over his wayes, the more carefull to ſerve and
pleaſe God, than ever he had beene in former times.
Whereupon ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> upon thoſe words
of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 8. Omnia cooperantur, &amp;c. All
things worke together for good to them that love God.
Etiam pecata Domine, Even our very ſinnes O Lord;</hi>
for by ſinne wee have experience of our infirmity,
our infirmity brings us downe to humility, humility
brings us home to God, and in God every man hath
his <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> a happy diſcharge from all his ſins.
This being done, one thing onely remaines, and
that is this; A man that hath ſinned of infirmity,
will labour to bring forth that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which
<hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſpeakes of, <hi>Mat. 3. 8. The worthy fruites
of repentance;</hi> for you moſt know, that repentance
is one thing, and the fruit of repentance is another;
it is not enough to repent, and be ſorry for what a
man hath done (ſo did <hi>Iudas,</hi> ſo did <hi>Ahab)</hi> but he
muſt honeſtly and unfainedly endeavour to bring
forth the fruit of repentance, and that is the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
and alteration of his life, and converſation
in the ſight of God and men. If it be thus with thee,
take comfort (in Gods name) from this comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Doctrine, that thou art no other then <hi>Eliah</hi> was,
a man ſubject to paſſion.</p>
            <p>It followes; <hi>Eliah was a man ſubject to paſsions,
yet he prayed;</hi> Hence we may learne, never to be ſo
dejected at the view of our frailties and imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
as to forbeare our reſorting to God in prayer.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16509:9"/>
For no man living hath ſo much neede to pray to
God, as a man ſubject to paſſions. It was one part
of <hi>Solomons</hi> requeſt to God, <hi>2 Chron. 6. 29. When
any one ſhall perceive and feele his owne ſore, his owne
griefe,</hi> and the Plague of his owne heart (as he ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
a mans owne corruption) what ſhall hee doe?
Shall he deſpaire, ſhall hee be driven backe from
God (as <hi>Iordan</hi> was driven backe at the preſence of
the <hi>Arke)</hi> no, let him doe this; let him downe
upon his knees to God, and ſpread forth his hands
to Heaven, and the Lord which dwelleth in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
will heare him, and when he heares, have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.
It was an amazed and unadviſed prayer, that of
<hi>Simon</hi> to our Saviour, <hi>Luke 5. 8.</hi> when hee cryed
out, <hi>Lord goe from me, for I am a ſinfull man;</hi> as if
a Patient ſhould ſay to the Phyſitian, depart from
mee, for I am ſicke. The ſicker a man is, the more
neede he hath of the Phyſitians preſence; and the
ſinfuller he is, the more neede to draw neere to his
Saviour: as a man that ſhivers of an Ague creepes
nearer and nearer to the fire. You know our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
gracious call, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary
and heavy laden, and I will eaſe you.</hi> Now (as Saint
<hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith,) every Chriſtian is <hi>Animal oneriferum,
a burden-bearing creature;</hi> not a Chriſtian upon earth
but hath ſome croſſe or other to clogge him, ſome
corruption or other to burthen him at times, and
lies heavy upon his heart; what then is to be done?
Shall hee lye downe like <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> and couch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
his burthen? Shall hee be diſheartened and
diſcouraged from reſorting and approaching to
God? God forbid; let him in Gods name come to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16509:9"/>
Ieſus Chriſt that cals him, with teares in his eyes,
with true griefe and godly ſorrow in his heart, with
humble confeſſions and prayers in his mouth; and
he hath promiſed <hi>in verbo ſervatoris,</hi> in the word
of a Saviour, that he will releaſe and eaſe him of it.
One thing I muſt tell thee by the way, when thou
prayeſt to Chriſt for eaſe, thou muſt promiſe him
obedience and ſervice; as the Iſraelites did to <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam,
1 Reg. 12. Eaſe us of our burthen, and we will
be thy ſervants for ever.</hi> Thus doe, and then let thy
burthen be never ſo great, thy corruptions never
ſo many, thy paſſions never ſo ſtrong; Hee that
could calme the ſea, can calme thy ſorrowes, and
ſpeake peace unto thy ſoule in the midſt of all thy
troubles, and therefore, if at any time thy paſſions
be ſtirred, and thy heart diſquieted within thee;
know of a ſurety, that, there is ſome <hi>Ionah</hi> that
hath raiſed this ſtorme, ſome ſinne or other that
hath cauſed this trouble to thy ſoule; then fall to
thy prayers (as <hi>Eliab</hi> did) and give God no reſt, till
God hath given reſt to thy ſoule. <hi>Eliah was a man
ſubject to paſsions, and he prayed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It followes, How did he pray? My Text ſaith, <hi>he
prayed earneſtly,</hi> in the Originall it is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>In praying he prayed,</hi> or, <hi>he prayed a prayer,</hi> we tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate
it, <hi>He prayed earneſtly,</hi> and it is to very good
purpoſe; for it implies thus much: that no prayer
is a prayer indeede, but an earneſt prayer. Cold
and careleſſe prayers, counterfeit and ſuperſtitious
prayers, they be but <hi>res nihili,</hi> in Gods account no
prayers at all. I will give you an inſtance, <hi>Act. 9.
11.</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> was converted and ſtricken with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16509:10"/>
blindneſſe, Almighty God ſent <hi>Ananias</hi> to him
to lay his hands upon him, and to recover him of
his fight; now leaſt he ſhould miſtake the man, and
lay his hands upon a wrong party, God gives him
this private token to know him by, <hi>forbehold he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi>
Now let mee demand; doe you thinke that
Saint <hi>Paul</hi> never prayed to God till that time? or
doe you imagine that was the firſt prayer that ever
Saint <hi>Paul</hi> made? It is the firſt wee reade of; but
doe you thinke hee never prayed before? I beleeve
he did many a time and oft; and I will give you my
reaſon: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (you know) was a Phariſee, one
of the ſtricteſt and devouteſt of all the Sect (as hee
teſtifies of himſelfe) and the Phariſees, you know,
were altogether given to long praying; it was their
glory and their gaine too, that they could make long
prayers in every place, in the open ſtreetes, in wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes
houſes; and no doubt but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had as
excellent a faculty that way, and could pray as long
and as largely as the beſt of them all: but ſee the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue:
Almighty God, who ſtiles himſelfe the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
of prayers, gave no eare, tooke no notice of all
his formall, Phariſaicall, hypocriticall prayers,
which he had made in former times; till hee came
to this humble, this earneſt, this heart-breaking
prayer; <hi>And now</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>Behold he prayeth;</hi> he
never prayed indeed, till now: for as <hi>Philo</hi> ſaith
well; God doth not <hi>numerare,</hi> but <hi>ponderare, not
number our prayers, but weigh them;</hi> if he finde them
cordiall, if hee finde them hearty, that they have
ſome ſubſtance, and ſome weight in them, then he
records and regiſters and ſets them downe in that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16509:10"/>
booke of remembrance which the Prophet ſpeakes
of, <hi>Mal. 3. 16.</hi> If otherwiſe, they be dull and heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,
lazy and ſpiritleſſe, God doth by them as he
doth by our ſinnes of ignorance, <hi>Act. 17. 30.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
winke at them, paſſe by, and take no notice of them;
let no man therefore deceive himſelfe to thinke that
all kinde of praying ſpeedes alike, for no prayer is a
prayer in Gods account, but an earneſt prayer, <hi>Eliah</hi>
prayed a prayer, becauſe he prayed earneſtly.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, it is worth your noting, to ſee the
conſtant diſpoſition of this holy man. <hi>Eliah</hi> was well
knowne to bee a hot ſpirited man in all his actions,
exceeding zealous and earneſt in all his reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
both of the King, and of the people. Now
here you may obſerve the equability, the evenneſſe
of <hi>Eliahs</hi> zeale; as he was earneſt in his reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
ſo he was as earneſt in his devotions; and as
zealous in his prayers, as he was in his anger. There
is many a man hot and fiery in his anger, but cold
and luke-warme in prayers; ſuch zeale is never
right. <hi>Gal. 4. 18. It is good to be alwayes earneſt in a
good thing.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the word to be hot and fiery,
and zealouſly affected in one good thing as well as
another, in devotion, as well as reprehenſion, in
prayer, as well as in anger. When a mans zeale is
equable (like <hi>Eliahs)</hi> then it is right and pleaſing to
God.</p>
            <p>As Phyſitians judge of the ſtate of a mans body,
<hi>Vniverſalia ſalutaria, particularia ex mo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bo;</hi> as thus:
if a man be hot in one part and cold in another; if the
palmes of his hands burne, and the ſoles of his feete
be key-cold, then all is not right; but if he be of an
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16509:11"/>
indifferent equall heate all over, that held a good
ſigne of good health in the body. By the like rule
judge thou of the ſtate of thy ſoule, if thy zeale be
equable and uniforme both in prayer and in anger,
it is a good ſigne of grace and ſanctification in thy
heart; but if it vary and differ, that there is too
much heate in the one, too little in the other; all is
not well within. It was the reaſon which old Father
<hi>Latimer</hi> gave, why men in theſe dayes doe not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile
with God in their prayers, as <hi>Eliah</hi> and ſuch
others had done in former times, <hi>Deeſt ignis</hi> (ſaith
he) <hi>deeſt ignis, There lackes fire, there lackes fire;</hi>
his meaning is, our prayers want that zeale, that
heate, that earneſtneſſe, which they put into theirs.
For as incenſe without fire yeelds no ſmell, no more
doth prayer without zeale and earneſtneſſe; and as
Hony is no Hony, if it have loſt its ſweetneſſe; and
Vinegar is no Vinegar, if it have loſt its ſharpeneſſe;
ſo Prayer is no Prayer, if it bee voide of earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<hi>Eliah</hi> prayed indeede, becauſe hee prayed
earneſtly.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the ſubject, and matter of his
Prayer which (I told you) was firſt for a judgement,
and then for a bleſſing, firſt for a drought, and then
for raine, as it followeth. <hi>Hee prayed earneſtly that it
might not raine, and it rained not on the earth by the
ſpace of three yeares and ſixe moneths.</hi> Here are two
weighty points to be conſidered. 1. What ſhould
moove <hi>Eliah</hi> to pray for a judgement. 2. Why he
made choiſe to pray for this kinde of judgement, of
drought and dearth, rather then for any other. I will
tell you my opinion of both.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:16509:11"/>
1. Vpon what ground, or by what warrant did
<hi>Eliah</hi> pray for a judgement. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit)
ſeemes to taxe him for it, <hi>Rom. 11. 2.</hi> and he
brings it in with a <hi>notandum, wote ye not (i.)</hi> doe ye
not marke and obſerve what the Scripture ſaith of
<hi>Eliah, how he made interceſsion to God againſt Iſrael.</hi>
Good men in former times were wont to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion
to God <hi>For</hi> the people, not <hi>Againſt</hi> them:
<hi>Abraham</hi> prayed for the wicked <hi>Sodomites, Ieremy</hi>
prayed for the Idolatrous <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> till God forbad
him, and gave him a countermand, <hi>Pray no more for
this people, for I will not heare thee, Ier. 11. 14.</hi> The
Husbandman in the Parable entreates his Maſter for
the unfruitfull tree, that he would ſpare it and not
cut it downe, and doth <hi>Eliah</hi> differ from all the reſt,
and bend his prayers againſt the people, and pray
for the vexation and undoing of his Country? How
could this ſtand with that good Religion, and that
good affection which ſo holy a man ſhould beare to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the people of God? Anſwer. Three things
there are (in my weake judgement) that may ſeeme
to warrant and beare out <hi>Eliah</hi> in praying for a
judgement.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Authoritas Prophetica,</hi> Prophets might doe
more then ordinary perſons, and <hi>Eliah</hi> had the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
of Propheſie, and knew by revelation from God,
that ſuch a judgement was a comming, therefore
he might the more warrantably and unoffenſively
frame his deſires to Gods appointments, and fit his
prayers to Gods purpoſes. Thus muſt we conceive
of thoſe bitter execrations and imprecations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<hi>David</hi> did ſo often in the Pſalmes curſe and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16509:12"/>
banne his enemies, <hi>[Let their Table be their ſnare,
let their children be vagabondes and begge their bread,
&amp;c.]</hi> A man would thinke it could not ſtand with
the piety and charity of a godly man, to wiſh ſuch
wicked events, ſuch uncharitable wiſhes to proceed
out of his mouth: but onely that we know, he was
a Prophet of God, and did it <hi>per afflatum divinum,
by the direction and inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> he
knew by the ſpirit of Propheſie, they were ſuch as
were accurſed of God, being Gods enemies as well
as his, and therefore might the more warrantably
and ſafely doe it. It is not for us to uſe <hi>Davids</hi> cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
unleſſe we had <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit. <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Eliah</hi>
had that gift which the Apoſtle cals <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>the diſcerning ſpirits;</hi> they knew by inſtinct from
heaven, who were bleſſed and who were curſed of
God. It is not ſo with us, God hath hid thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets
from our eyes, and therefore it is our part and
duty to pray in love and charity, <hi>That God would
have mercy upon all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what uſe then are we to make of thoſe curſes
in the Pſalmes that are read ſo often to us? Anſwer,
Thus we may doe, we may apply them to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
of the Church, that ſeeke the ruine of the true
Religion, and profeſſe an open enmity to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
and faith of Ieſus Chriſt (Who is God bleſſed for
ever) we may ſafely take our Saviours part, and curſe
all thoſe that are enemies to him: <hi>[So let all thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
periſh, O Lord, Iud. 5. 31.]</hi> But for our owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
that have done us ſome private wrong, or
bare us ſome ſecret grudge, to curſe them and ban
them in this kinde (as the uſuall manner of ſome is)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16509:12"/>
it is both unwarrantable, uncharitable, and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
But the beſt and ſafeſt uſe, that we can make of
thoſe curſes, is to appropriate and apply them to
our ſelves, to acknowledge and adjudge our ſelves
worthy to undergoe all thoſe deadly evils, and that
God may juſtly doe ſo; and more than ſo unto us,
if hee ſhould deale with us according to our ſinnes;
by this meanes we ſhall ſave God a labour, and our
ſelves a paine. For as on the contrary, to bleſſe our
ſelves is the way to make God curſe us, <hi>Deut. 29.
20. Hee that bleſſeth himſelfe when hee heareth the
words of theſe curſes, ſaying, I ſhall have peace though
I walke in the imagination of my owne heart, adding
drunkenneſſe to thirſt.</hi> (marke what followes) <hi>The
Lord will be revenged upon the ſoule of ſuch a one, his
anger and his jealouſie ſhall ſmoke againſt that man, and
all the curſes that are written in this booke ſhall light
upon him, and the Lord ſhall blot out his name from
under Heaven.</hi> This a man gets by bleſſing of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:
whereas if thou wouldſt be bleſt of God, I
doe not ſay, that thou ſhouldſt curſe thy ſelfe (farre
be it from any ſervant of Chriſt ſo to doe) but this
I would adviſe thee to doe, even with a ſorrowfull
and a ſad heart, to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to all the curſes in the
Booke of God, to acknowledge and confeſſe that
thou haſt juſtly deſerved, and that it is Gods onely
mercy that thou haſt eſcaped them. So much for
the firſt reaſon that may warrant <hi>Eliahs</hi> prayer; the
next may be this.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Convenientia temporis,</hi> the fitneſſe and order
of time when this was done, it was done in the time
of the Law, which was uſed to ſuch judgements,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16509:13"/>
they were then accuſtomed to more terrible won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
than are now ſutable to the ſweete and ſaving
time of the Goſpel; obſerve the wonders that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
wrought in <hi>Egypt,</hi> what terrible, what hurtfull,
what miſchievous wonders they were, he turned all
their water into blood, all their duſt into Lice, and
ſpoyled all the fruits of the earth, and undid the
whole Land. What a dreadfull wonder was that
of <hi>Eliſha, 2 Reg. 2.</hi> when he curſed the children of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel,</hi>
that mocked him for his baldneſſe: One would
have thought that a little diſcipline, a little correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
or ſending to their Parents or Maſters, would
have ſufficed, and beene a ſufficient revenge for
waggiſh unhappy boyes, that did not know their
duty to a man of God: but hee lookes upon them
with a direfull countenance, and <hi>curſed</hi> and banned
<hi>them in the name of the Lord,</hi> and immediately <hi>two
Shee-beares came out of the Wood, and tare two and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of them in pieces:</hi> what a horrible, what a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
what a miſcheivous wonder was this? Of the
ſame kind was that of <hi>Eliah, 2 Reg. 1.</hi> When the
Captaine came with authority, to bid him come
downe, and come before the King; he might have
anſwered, I cannot come, or the Lord appointed
me ſome other way to goe, &amp;c. but the next word
we heare, is a word of Iudgement and Vengeance,
<hi>If I be a man of God, let fire come downe from heaven,
and conſume thee, and thy company:</hi> and ſo it did both
them, and the reſt that came after on the ſame meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.
Such wonders as theſe were uſuall in the time
of the Law. But now looke to the Miracles and
Wonders of our Saviour in the Goſpell, and you
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16509:13"/>
ſhall finde them to be of another nature, all of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
and mercy, all mercifull, all beneficiall, all
healing Miracles, no way hurtfull or deſtructive of
any mans life. We read of many a mans life that he
ſaved, many that hee recalled and reſtored, none
that he deſtroyed, no not one: being ſo reviled as
he was, ſo perſecuted, ſo laid for, ſo betrayed, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended,
condemned and crucified; yet what
one man did our Saviour ſtrike dead for all theſe
haynous indignities? Nay, he was ſo farre from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,
that he prayed for their lives that ſought and
wrought his death.</p>
            <p>The moſt terrible wonders that ever our Saviour
did, were but two, and thoſe no wayes prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
to the perſon or life of any man, woman, or
childe. The one was his <hi>curſing</hi> and blaſting of <hi>the
barren Figge-tree;</hi> and this was but ſymbolicall,
not done in any ſpleene to the poore tree; but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to ſhew his indignation againſt all unfruitfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion;
when men make an outward ſhew of piety
to God; but when the poore and hungry come to
them (as Chriſt came to that Figge-tree) hoping
to pull ſome fruite of charity and mercy from them,
there is nothing to be found but leaves, good words
perhaps, and that is all: beleeve it, ſuch men are
nigh unto curſing, and it is Gods infinite mercy, if
he doe not blaſt their eſtate (as Chriſt did the Fig-tree)
that it ſhall never proſper to them nor theirs.
The other wonder of Chriſt that did any hurt, was
that, <hi>Matth. 8. The drowning of the Swine,</hi> and yet
that was the devils doing, Chriſt onely gave way
to theſe evill ſpirits (which ſeeke the deſtruction of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16509:14"/>
man and beaſt) to carry them headlong into the ſea
(as they would carry us too, but that God above,
who ſtiles himſelfe <hi>The preſerver of men,</hi> is pleaſed
in mercy to keepe out of their clutches;) and this
was ſymbolicall too, to let us underſtand how God
hates all thoſe that are of a <hi>ſwiniſh diſpoſition;</hi> that
is, all drunken ſots, that like ſwine, have neither
wit nor grace to moderate themſelves in the uſe of
Gods creatures; and all lazy beaſts that minde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but their bellies, (as you know) a Swine is
one of the lazieſt creatures that a man can keepe, it
doth him no worke, nor ſervice at all; or laſtly,
All hoggiſh worldlings, and miſerable mucke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes
of the earth, that never doe good till they
come to dye: let all ſuch tremble and feare, and
call to God for mercy, leaſt in his juſt judgement he
deliver their ſoules into the hands of thoſe helliſh
Fiends to carry them headlong (as they did the
Swine) <hi>into the lake that burneth with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone
for evermore, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing
of teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the two ſevereſt wonders that ever our
Saviour did, or ſuffered to be done; as for all the
reſt (looke into the Stories of the Goſpell, which
are the Acts and Monuments of Ieſus Chriſt) you
ſhall finde to be all gracious, all beneficiall, all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
and ſaving wonders. Never any man came to
him for ſight, that went away blind; never any
came to him for hearing, that went away deafe;
never any came to him for health, that went away
ſicke. In a word, you ſhall never finde that ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
man or woman came to our Saviour for any helpe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16509:14"/>
or mercy, that ever went away confounded or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed
of their hopes. Now beloved, Chriſt is
the ſame Ieſus ſtill, that then hee was: <hi>Coelum non
animum</hi> (as wee ſay) though hee have changed his
place, he hath not changed his nature, but is ſtill as
favourable, as indulgent to mankind as ever he was,
if we doe but as truely ſeeke unto him for our ſoules
health, as they did for their bodies.</p>
            <p>So you ſee the nature of theſe wonders is altered
from that they were in <hi>Eliahs</hi> times: the ſeverity
of the Law ſuites not with the lenity of the Goſpell;
and wee muſt now imitate our Saviour in workes of
mercy, and not follow <hi>Eliah</hi> in prayers for judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
Wee ſee, <hi>Luke 9. 54.</hi> When the Diſciples
fingers itched to be revenged on the <hi>Samaritans</hi> for
their baſe diſcourteſie in not entertaining our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our;
<hi>Maſter,</hi> (ſaith they) <hi>wilt thou that we command
fire from Heaven, and conſume them, as Eliah did?</hi>
Wee have a preſident for it, it is a booke caſe, <hi>Eliah</hi>
did ſo, let us doe the like, theſe men deſerve it, as
bad or worſe than they with whom <hi>Eliah</hi> had to
doe: <hi>No,</hi> (ſaith our Saviour, the caſe is altered) <hi>ye
know not of what ſpirit ye are;</hi> the ſpirit of the Law
required ſeverity, the ſpirit of the Goſpell requires
meekeneſſe and mercy. Farre is it from the good
Spirit of Chriſt and of God, to ſtirre up any mans
heart to private revenge; not an Eagle, but a Dove
was the ſhape wherein that holy and healthfull Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
made choiſe to appeare. Let us therefore all that
are called Chriſtians, follow no other preſident, but
our Saviour Chriſts; whoſe onely leſſon that ever
he ſet us to learne of him, was this, to be humble and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16509:15"/>
meeke, and ſo doing we ſhall find <hi>Requiem animabus;
reſt and peace to our owne ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt reaſon that may warrant <hi>Eliah</hi>
in praying for a judgement, was,</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Neceſsitas rei, the neceſsity of the thing it ſelfe;</hi>
that holy Prophet had ſpent his ſtrength in vaine,
Sermon upon Sermon, warning upon warning,
threatning upon threatning; and when he ſaw that
nothing would worke them to goodneſſe, then he
prayes for a judgement; not in a vindictive way to
be revenged upon them, but as a deſperate remedy,
knowing that that or nothing would bring them to
good, as it is ſaid, <hi>2 Chron. ult.</hi> God ſent his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
<hi>riſing early and ſending them,</hi> and uſed all gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
meanes to reclaime them, <hi>till there was no remedy,</hi>
then he ſent deſtruction. In this ſence, if a man have
a child or a friend, or any one that he wiſheth well
to his ſoule; if he be growne to that paſſe, ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
in ſinne, that no perſwaſions, no warnings, no
threatnings will worke upon him; I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
it were neither uncharitable, nor unpleaſing to
God, if a man ſhould pray, Lord ſmite him, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
him, lay ſome medicinall, ſome healing pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
upon him, that hee may ſee the errour
of his wayes, and may returne and repent, and ſo be
ſaved.</p>
            <p>Vpon theſe and the like grounds, I ſuppoſe <hi>Eliah</hi>
might with a ſafe conſcience pray for a judgement:
but then the next queſtionis, Why he ſhould make
choiſe to pray for this kind of judgment, of drought
and dearth, for want of raine; rather then any other.
I will tell you what I thinke the reaſons may be.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:16509:15"/>
1. Becauſe it was an uncontrouleable, a convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
judgement; if <hi>Eliah</hi> ſhould have brought any
earthly or viſible judgement, as Sword or Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
&amp;c. they would have imputed it preſently to
ſome ſecondary meanes and cauſes; now this was
a heavenly an inviſible judgement, the ſtoppage of
the clouds, the detaining of Raine, and the burning
and ſcorching of the Sunne; was a judgement from
heaven, and ſuch as they muſt needes confeſſe to be
<hi>Digitus, the finger of God,</hi> not <hi>Aliquid humani,</hi> no
handy worke of any mortall man. For this was the
fallacy which the Scribes and Phariſees put upon
our Saviour <hi>Math. 16. 1.</hi> When they had ſeene all
the miracles and wonders of Chriſt, how he cured
the ſicke, &amp;c. they conceited that theſe things
might be done by ſlight of hand, by Art of Magicke,
by <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> or by Conjuration, &amp;c. but (ſay they)
<hi>Shew us a ſigne from heaven; and then we will beleeve.</hi>
They knew that a Magician or a devill might doe
much upon earth, but he could doe nothing in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;
therefore (ſay they) <hi>ſhew us a ſigne from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
and we will beleeve.</hi> So here to prevent all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceites,
<hi>Elias</hi> prayed and procures a judgement
from heaven; and that a convincing a cutting judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
for you muſt know that the people at that
time left off to worſhip the true God, and fell to
worſhip <hi>Baall,</hi> the Sunne, the Moone, and all the
Hoaſt of Heaven; truſting no doubt that theſe gods
of theirs, would by their influence ſo moyſten and
fatten the earth, that they ſhould not need to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding
to God for any raine: now (quoth <hi>Eliah)</hi>
here is a judgement to try yours gods withall, goe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16509:16"/>
to the gods that ye have ſerved, let them helpe now
or never, if they can doe any thing, they can ſend a
ſhowre of rayne, if not, why doe ye ſerve them?
I ſay it was a convincing judgement. <hi>Eliah</hi> did it on
purpoſe, to let them ſee the vileneſſe of their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
what baſe, what impotent, what unworthy
gods they ſerved, that could not helpe their clyents
to a droppe of raine. In like manner, whatſoever a
man makes his god, beſides the true one; I meane,
puts his truſt in, for helpe in time of neede; ſhall
at length ſo deceive him, and ſo befoole him, that
hee ſhall bee forced to confeſſe, as theſe people
did in the end; <hi>The Lord he is God, The Lord hee is
God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Becauſe it was a juſt and a fitting puniſhment;
this people were guilty of ſpirituall barrenneſſe, and
God plagued them with temporall barrenneſſe. No
Nation under heaven was ſo husbanded, and manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
of God, ſo watered with the dewes of heaven,
I meane, with the meanes of grace and ſalvation, as
they were, and yet none more unfruitfull in every
good worke: Now therefore <hi>Eliah</hi> fits them with
a judgement ſutable and agreeable to their ſinne: he
prayes to God that it might not raine, that ſo their
lands might be anſwerable to their lives, and their
foyles become as barren as their ſoules. Thus it
pleaſeth God many times to pay men in their owne
coyne, to come home to them in their owne kinde,
and to fit his puniſhments according to their ſinnes.
That as they that ſinne in their goods, by miſget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
miskeeping, and miſpending them, are many
times puniſhed in their goods, by loſſes, and croſſes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16509:16"/>
by fire, by water, &amp;c. And as they that ſinne in their
children, by miſloving, or miſnurturing them, are
oft times puniſhed in their children, as <hi>David</hi> was
in <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Adonijah;</hi> ſo they that ſinne in
their lands: it is juſt with God to puniſh them in
their lands: <hi>Solomon</hi> tels us, <hi>Prov. 21. 4.</hi> that <hi>the
plowing of a wicked man is ſinne,</hi> That is ſtrange; the
husbandry and tillage of the ground is generally
held to be one of the moſt honeſt, the moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,
the moſt harmeleſſe callings in the world; and
ſo it is of it ſelfe; and yet wee ſee, when a wicked
man takes the plow in hand; when a man goes to his
plow with an ill minde, and an ill conſcience, his
very plowing addes to his ſinnes. And it is juſt with
God, that that land which is plowed ſinfully, ſhould
thrive accordingly, and become as bad and as bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren
as the owner. <hi>A fruitfull land doth God make
barren, for the wickedneſſe of them that dwell therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Becauſe it was a ſenſible, and a palpable judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
As God Almighty told <hi>Caine, Gen. 4. 7.</hi> that
<hi>hee ſhould be curſed from the earth.</hi> The Lord knew
that <hi>Caine</hi> cared not to be curſed from heaven, and
to be baniſhed from the preſence of God, and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
for a Reprobate; but to bee curſed from the
earth, to be curſed in earthly things (hee being a
tiller of the earth) that would goe neareſt to his
heart of any judgement. Even ſuch is the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of every man of the earth (as <hi>David</hi> termes earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
minded men) they doe not value nor care to be
curſed from heaven, to be excommunicated out of
the favour of God, and out of the bleſſed company
of all faithfull people (which cenſure of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16509:17"/>
if it be rightly carryed with a <hi>Clave non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante</hi>
(as the Schoolemen ſpeake) when there is no
errour committed in the uſe of the keyes, is one of
the greateſt puniſhments under heaven.) But carnall
men are not ſenſible of this, and therefore God will
puniſh them in that wherein they are ſenſible, in
their wives and children, in their corne and cattell,
&amp;c. in ſuch things as are neereſt and deareſt to them:
as when <hi>David</hi> ſlung his ſtone at <hi>Goliah,</hi> if hee had
ſtrucke him upon any part of his harneſſe, hee had
never felt the blow, but ſtriking him (as hee did) in
the forehead, which was naked and tender, that
ſunke him preſently; ſo it is with carnall men, for
ſpirituall judgements, they are harneſſed, their hearts
are hardned, their conſciences are ſeared, they have
(as the Apoſtle ſpeakes) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a horny hoofe
(as it were) growne over their hearts, that makes
them inſenſible of any ſpirituall blow that can light
upon them. Therefore Almighty God, knowing in
what part they lie naked, in what kinde they are ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly
affected, namely, in their affection to earthly
things, ſtrikes them there, plagues them in that,
and that ſinkes them like <hi>Nabal,</hi> whoſe heart dyed
within him like a ſtone. As we ſee in <hi>Exodus,</hi> how
<hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> hardned their heart, and
out ſtood all the plagues of <hi>Egypt,</hi> till God plagued
them in their children, and that broke their hearts.
So beleeve it, they that care not for ſpirituall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments
(for the loſſe of Gods favour, the loſſe of
heaven, the loſſe and perill of their owne ſoules)
God will finde a time to puniſh them in that which
they doe and ſhall care for, in their corne, in their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16509:17"/>
ſubſtance, in that which is neereſt and deareſt to
them: As he did theſe <hi>Iſraelies</hi> here, becauſe they
were not ſenſible of the want of grace. God puniſht
them with that would make them ſenſible, with the
want of raine; that when they had plowed and
ſowne their land, and beſtowed all their care and
coſt, all ſhould be in vaine, for want of moiſture to
refreſh the earth. Theſe or the like reaſons (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe)
might moove <hi>Eliah</hi> to pray and procure this
kinde of judgement.</p>
            <p>By the way, if any man deſire to know the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
why God is not thus marveilous in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
of the Goſpell, as hee was in <hi>Eliah,</hi> and thoſe
other Prophets of the Law; why wee that are his
Evangelicall Prophets cannot doe ſuch wonders in
our dayes, as they did in theirs? Anſwer, though
that ſame <hi>donum miraculorum,</hi> the gift of Miracles
be ceaſed in the Church, now that the Goſpell hath
taken roote: as Husbandmen when they tranſplant a
tree, at firſt, they ſet props and ſtayes to ſhore it up,
but after it hath taken root, they take away the ſtaies
and let it grow by the ordinary influence of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens;)
I ſay though the gift of working wonders be
ceaſed, yet miracles &amp; wonders in another kind ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verceaſe,
but are wrought daily by the Preachers of
the Goſpell. For you muſt know that the miracles
under the Goſpell are of a differing nature from the
miracles under the Law: thoſe were <hi>ocularia mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula</hi>
(as I may fitly call them) <hi>eye-miracles,</hi> that
were viſible and outwardly apparent to be ſeene;
but theſe are <hi>Auricularia miracula, Eare-miracles,</hi>
ſecret and inviſible, wrought in the heart by the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16509:18"/>
Word and Spirit of God, entring in at the eare, and
going downe into the ſoule. Though wee cannot
command, or forbid the raine to water the earth, as
<hi>Eliah</hi> did; if we can water and mollifie the earthen
hearts of men with the ſupernaturall raine of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
Doctrine, and make a dry and barren ſoule
beare fruit to God; is not this as great a wonder as
the other? Though we cannot cauſe nor command
the thunder (as <hi>Samuel</hi> did) to terrifie the people for
their ſinnes; yet God hath his <hi>Boanerges,</hi> his ſons
of thunder ſtill, that by ratling from heaven the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
judgements of God againſt ſinne and ſinners,
are able to make the ſtouteſt and the proudeſt heart
upon earth, even tremble and quake, and fall downe
before the preſence of God; and is not this as great
a miracle as that of <hi>Samuel,</hi> to bring an unhumbled
ſinner upon his knees, and make glad to cry God
mercy for his ſinnes? In a word, though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
caſt out devils out of mens bodies, as the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
of Chriſt could doe; if wee can caſt the devill
out of mens ſoules, by the powerfull Goſpell of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt; is it not as great a wonder? Beleeve it
brethren, the converſion of a ſinner to God, and
bringing of a ſoule to heaven, is abſolutely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
compariſon the greateſt miracle, the greateſt
wonder in the world. And theſe be the miracles
wherewith it pleaſeth God to grace the Miniſters
of the Goſpell; therefore ye obſerve, that the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
for Miniſters, runs thus, <hi>Almighty God which only
workeſt great marvels, &amp;c.</hi> When a ſoule is ſicke to
the death, with a ſurfeit of ſinne, is recovered and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived
againe by that ſame healthfull ſpirit of grace,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16509:18"/>
which God together with his Word doth breathe
into the ſoule, it is ſo great a marvell, ſo rare a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
that the Angels of heaven rejoyce to ſee it.</p>
            <p>I have held you over-long in the former part of
<hi>Eliahs</hi> prayer, which brought the judgement: heare
now in a word or two, the Reverſing of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and I have done. <hi>[And hee prayed againe, and
the heavens gave raine, and the earth brought forth her
fruit.]</hi> It well becomes the Prophets of God to be
mercifull; Good <hi>Eliah</hi> had not the heart to hold
the people too long under a judgement, when hee
ſaw he had done enough to humble them, he deſires
God to reverſe the judgement. As it is obſerved of
the good Angels in the old and new Teſtament,
when they appeared to any, either man, or woman;
their method and manner was this, <hi>Primo terrent,
deinde laetificant,</hi> they firſt terrified them, and put
them into feare, then preſently comforted them,
and put them out of feare. Thus did <hi>Eliah</hi> with
this people; thus did <hi>Moſes</hi> with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that
good man had not the heart to hold wicked <hi>Pharaoh</hi>
alway under a judgement, but upon the leaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty
made ſuite to God to reverſe it. So dealt the
Prophet with <hi>Ieroboam, 1 Reg. 13. 6.</hi> when hee had
ſmitten him with a judgement, and had him at the
advantage, that his hand was witnered, <hi>Ieroboam</hi>
was glad to ſubmit and ſay, <hi>Intreate now the face of
the Lord thy God, and pray for me, that my hand may
be restored me:</hi> The man of God had not the heart
to deny him, but immediately, beſought the Lord,
and the Kings hand was reſtored, and became as it
was before. When a judgement comes, then Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16509:19"/>
are in ſeaſon. <hi>Abraham</hi> is better than a King
in this caſe, <hi>Gen. 20. 7. Reſtore the man his owne, for
he is a Prophet, and hee ſhall pray for thee;</hi> and ver.
17. <hi>Abraham prayed unto God, and God healed Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech,
&amp;c. Goe to my ſervant Iob</hi> (ſaith God to his
friends, <hi>Iob 42. 8.) and my ſervant Iob ſhall pray for
you, for him will I accept.</hi> So <hi>Act. 8. 24.</hi> When <hi>Peter</hi>
had denounced a curſe on <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> he was glad
to crouch and cry unto him, <hi>Oh pray yee to the Lord
for me, that none of theſe things which ye have ſpoken
come upon mee.</hi> Thus yee ſee that judgements and
plagues will bring Prophets into requeſt: men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
deale with their Miniſters, as boyes doe by
Walnut-trees, and other fruit-trees, in faire wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
throw cudgels at us, in foule runne to us for
ſhelter. In the dayes of peace and proſperity wee
are paſt over as ſuperfluous creatures, of whom
there is little uſe, and leſſe neede: but when the
wrath of God fals on the naked ſoule, when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
is wounded within, and body pained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,
then the Miniſter is thought on. I ſay no more,
if you deſire their prayers, and that God ſhould heare
them praying for you in your extremity, doe not
ſlight them, doe not wrong them in proſperity. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
how <hi>Ahab</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> were glad to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden
to <hi>Eliah</hi> to reverſe their judgement; and you
do not know how ſoone the caſe may be your owne:
therefore as you love your ſoules, love thoſe that
have charge of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And he prayed againe, &amp;c.</hi> When I looke into the
Story, <hi>1 Reg. 18.</hi> I can finde no direct prayer that
<hi>Eliah</hi> made for raine. But I finde there a twofold
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16509:19"/>
prayer that he made. 1. A vertuall. 2. A formall
prayer.</p>
            <p>1. A Vertuall prayer, not for raine, but for their
converſion. <hi>Oh Lord,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eliah) bring backe, or
bring home the heart of this people unto thee; verſ. 73.</hi>
and this includes all other prayers that can be made:
A prayer for converſion is a prayer for every thing,
<hi>Ier. 31. 18.</hi> When <hi>Ephraim</hi> prayes for converſion,
<hi>Turne thou me, and I ſhall be turned:</hi> (ſaith God)
<hi>I will ſurely have mercy upon him &amp;c.</hi> Such is the
goodneſſe of God, that he will with-hold no good
thing, (be it raine, be it plenty, be it any thing that
is good for them) from them that are converted,
and brought home by true repentance to him.
Therefore if thou ſtandeſt in need of any temporall
mercy, pray firſt for converſion, and all other good
things ſhall be ſuper-added and throwne in unto
thee; or if thou prayeſt for any child, or for any
friend to doe him good indeed, pray for his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
and thou prayeſt for every thing, that one
prayer is <hi>inſtar omnium, inſteed of all the reſt.</hi> If he
be in an ill way, deſire God to bring him backe, and
for future things take no care.</p>
            <p>2. A formall prayer, when he ſaw that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
were truely humbled, and that their hearts were
indeed brought home to God, inſomuch that they
cryed out, with an ingemmination, <hi>The Lord hee is
God, the Lord he is God,</hi> then he buckles his head be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
his knees (to ſhew the humble proſtration
of his ſoule) and fals a praying to God for raine.
After humiliation any prayer comes in ſeaſon, <hi>Eſay
1. Waſh ye, make ye cleane, put away the evill of your
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16509:20"/>
doings, &amp;c. And now come</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and wee will
reaſon together,</hi> now let us parle, now let us confeſſe,
now pray and I will heare you. <hi>Iud. 10. 17.</hi> When
the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> put away their ſtrange gods, and turned
themſelves to the true God by ſincere repentance
and reformation; the Text ſaith, <hi>His ſoule was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
for the miſery of Iſrael:</hi> thus the onely way to
caſe our owne ſoules of griefe, or to be rid of any
grievous judgement, is to <hi>grieve the ſoule of God,</hi> that
is, to humble our ſelves before him, to pray and
ſeeke his face, and to turne from our wicked wayes,
and God will be even grieved with himſelfe that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
he puniſhed, plagued, and put us to griefe; and
he will returne (as he ſaith) and have mercy on us,
and will do us good after he hath done us hurt. Here
then (in a word) is the ready way to prevaile with
God, either for raine, or for faire weather, or for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
temporall bleſſing whatſoever, to doe as <hi>Eliah</hi>
did, buckle our very heads betweene our knees, I
meane, proſtrate our ſelves before the face of God,
in the humbleſt, in the lowlieſt, in the moſt dejected
manner that we can device, and if any meanes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
heaven will fetch downe mercy from heaven,
that will doe it. <hi>Eliah prayed againe, and the heavens
gave raine, and the earth brought forth her fruit.</hi> Now
to God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Ghoſt, be aſcribed and given, all honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
be done and performed all ſervice and duty, from
this time forth for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
